All right, good morning. The subject of today is דף מ"ו, Daf
Mem-Vav, we start on עמוד ב' Amud Beis at the גמרא Gemara
after having read the משנה, Mishna, which is משנה Mishna basically about
the age of adulthood, 12 and 13 for a girl and boy
respectively, but the year before is considered the מופלא סמוך לאיש, Mufleh
Samuch L'ish, the year before in which an act of making a
vow, a נדר Neder and related acts of verbal acts can be
performed if they know what they are doing. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. The משנה, Mishna, however, though was a
little bit redundant and the גמרא Gemara picks up on this. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, 10 lines down, וכיוון דתנא בת
אחת עשרה שנה ויום אחד נדריה נבדקין, V'keivan detana bas achas esrei
shanah ve-yom echad nedareha nivdakin, since you tell me that when she
is 11 years and a day in her 12th year you check
her vows to see if she knows what she's talking about, בת
שתים עשרה שנה ויום אחד נדריה קיימין למה לי, Bas shtei esrei
shanah ve-yom echad nedareha kayamin lama li, why do you bother saying
that at 12 years and a day they're good? I mean anyway
they'd be good the year before. Now that's already an easy answer.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I might have thought בודקין לעולם,
Bodkin l'olam, maybe even after she becomes an adult, 12 years and
a day, you have to check to make sure that she knows
what she's talking about. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that you
don't. Once she's an adult it's assumed and she can't even claim
that she doesn't know what she's talking about. Okay, now we know
why you need to tell me 11 and a day and 12
and a day. But וכיוון דתנא י"ב שנה ויום אחד נדריה קיימין,
V'keivan detana yud-beis shanah ve-yom echad nedareha kayamin, once you tell me
that the terminal point is 12 years and a day, I mean
and then it's good
regardless, בודקין כל שתים עשרה למה לי, Bodkin kol shtei esrei lama
li, why do you have to tell me the entire 12th year
you check? You've already told me 11 and a day you check,
you've told me 12 and a day you don't need to check.
So of course you check the entire 12th year. So why are
you telling it to me? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I
might have thought, hold on, מר אמר ל' יום בשנה חשוב שנה,
Mar amar lamed yom b'shanah chashuv shanah, since we said yesterday there's
an opinion that 30 days in a year counts as a year,
and that might even be for these issues of ages, like רבי
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, two years and 30 days etc. So since there
is that opinion,
even though I said explicitly not that way, you need to be
12 years and a day for it to be good regardless, but
nevertheless I would have said that that plays a role.
היכא דבת כ' ל' ולא ידעה להפלות, Heicha d'bas kaf lamed v'lo
yad'ah l'haflos, maybe for the first 30 days of her 12th year
from 11 and a day for the next 30 days she doesn't
know what, she's made vows and she doesn't know what she's talking
about, so I might think that that represents the entire rest of
the year. And that rest of the year therefore she's not even
entitled to have her vows checked. We'll say look, for the first
30 days of this year you didn't know what you were talking
about, that's going to be your status for the entire year. So
I might have thought that that defines a status and therefore she
cannot have it checked later in the year. קא משמע לן Ka
mashma lan not that way, that anytime she makes a vow during
her 12th year, no matter how much she was ignorant at the
beginning, if she knows now what she's talking about or he knows
now, it's good. Okay, so that's why it says you check the
entire year. ליתני הני תרתי, Lisni hani tarti, let's just say those
two things. בת י"ב שנה ויום אחד נדריה קיימין ובודקין כל י"ב.
Bas yud-beis shanah ve-yom echad nedareha kayamin u-vodkin kol yud-beis. Say at
12 years and a day it's definitely good and you check the
entire 12th year. בת י"א שנה ויום אחד נדריה נבדקין למה לי,
Bas yud-aleph shanah ve-yom echad nedareha nivdakin lama li, why do you
have to say once you say you check the entire 12th year,
why do you say you check starting at 11 years and a
day? We've already said you check the entire 12th year so to
say the starting point is implied. So איצטריך, Itzterich, you need it.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I might have thought סתמא בשתים
עשרה בעיא בדיקה, Stama b'shtei esrei ba'ya bdika, in a normal case
at the 12th year you check, ובאחת עשרה לא בעיא בדיקה, U'v'achas
esrei lo ba'ya bdika, and at the 11th year you don't need
to check, or not you don't, checking, like, doesn't serve a purpose
because that's the normal case that checking is not meaningful in the
11th year.
But היכא דחזינא לה דחריפא טפי, Heicha d'chazina lah d'charifa t'fai, I
might have said the only reason you don't check at the 11th
year, meaning from 10 and a day until 11, the only reason
you don't check is like why bother, it's clear she won't know
what she's talking about. But I might have thought that if you
see that she's a highly intelligent young girl you would check even
in the 11th year, even from 10 years and a day, maybe
you're able to check if she would know. קא משמע לן Ka
mashma lan that it tells you not that way. So the point
is why did they tell you the entire 12th year to check?
To tell you that anytime during that period she's entitled to check.
Why did it have to say the beginning point, 11 years and
a day? To make it very clear that that is the terminal
point, that you cannot go any earlier than 11 years and a
day. Okay and therefore you said both, you start at 11 years
and a day to check, meaning before that it's not negotiable no
matter how smart she is. You end checking at 12 years and
a day because at that point you don't need to check, it's
definitely good. And you're able to check the entire middle period and
you have to say all those three things. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara
says, קודם זמן זה ואחר זמן זה למה לי? Kodem zman zeh
v'achar zman zeh lama li? Fine, once you tell me 11 and
a day you start, 12 and a day you don't check anymore,
you check the duration, why then you have to again say before
11 and a day it doesn't work, after... after twelve and a
day it doesn't it's not necessary? I mean come on, that's already
implied. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach amina, I would have thought הני
מילי היכא דלא קאמר אינש, hani mili heicha d'lo ka'amar inish, that's
only in cases where they're not explicitly claiming or reporting the opposite.
That's where prior to eleven and a day nothing works and after
twelve and a day we don't undermine it when there's not an
explicit claim to the opposite. אבל היכא דקאמר אינש, Aval heicha d'ka'amar
inish, but where they explicitly say otherwise, they're under eleven and a
day and they say I know exactly what I was talking about,
you can give me a test, or they're over twelve years and
a day and they say I have no idea what I was
talking about. You might think that when there's an explicit claim things
change. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan no, these הלכות halachot are
regardless of whatever they're claiming, that's the הלכה. halacha. Twelve and a
day it's definitely good, under eleven and a day it's no good
regardless, and in the interim period it's based on checking. Okay so
it deals a little bit with the redundancy, at the end of
the day it still feels somewhat redundant, but the גמרא Gemara is
very aware of that and tries to explain what it is why
it is there to clarify any possible other read. Now we get
to looking at some of the
הלכה. halacha. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught, אלו דברי רבי,
elu divrei Rabbi, these are the words of Rabbi, that a girl
goes by twelve years and a boy by thirteen, which is obviously
as you know how we פוסקן. pasken. אבל Aval רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, but Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says, now here's why you learn גמרא Gemara because if somebody would
tell you do you know some people say that a girl's בת
מצוה bat mitzvah is thirteen and a boy's בר מצוה bar mitzvah
is twelve you would say they're totally crazy. So let's take a
look. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer says דברים האמורים
בתינוקת בתינוק אמורים. devarim ha'amurim b'tinoket b'tinok amurim. What you're telling me
about a girl, twelve years old, is true about a boy. He
is of the age of majority at
twelve. דברים האמורים בתינוק בתינוקת אמורים, Devarim ha'amurim b'tinok b'tinoket amurim, that's
what's true about a girl, a girl is age of majority is
thirteen. You got it reversed. Okay, it's pretty clear we don't פוסקן
pasken that way. Now, אמר רב חסדא מאי טעמא דרבי? Amar Rav
Hisda mai ta'ama d'Rabbi? What's the reason of Rabbi? דכתיב, Dechtiv, right,
why are girls בת מצוה bat mitzvah earlier? So we would normally
say, well their physical body matures sooner. Okay, but it's not just
their physical body. Let's see what Rabbi says. דכתיב ויבן ה׳ אלהים
את הצלע, Dechtiv vayiven Hashem Elokim et hatzela, God built up the
side or the rib or the side into woman. מלמד, Melamed, that
right, the side that was taken from אדם. Adam. מלמד שנתן
הקדוש ברוך הוא בינה
יתירה. Melamed shenatan Hakadosh Baruch Hu binah yeteirah. The word ויבן, Vayiven,
בינה binah is build, also בינה binah understanding. God gave greater wisdom,
greater understanding באישה יותר מבאיש b'ishah yoteir m'ba'ish in a woman more
than in a man. Now sometimes this is, you know, quoted to
speak about like woman's intuition, greater insight that women have. Here it
might be that that is also the meaning. Here the purpose is
specifically about not really like they're smarter than men, but that it's
extra in the sense that it begins earlier. It starts already a
year earlier at twelve and by men it only starts at thirteen.
So here what the גמרא Gemara is saying based on a פסוק
pasuk and presumably reflecting a reality as well, an observed reality, is
that, you know, not only do girls' bodies mature quicker but also
girls tend to be, you know, more serious and because their minds
are maturing quicker as well, the maturity in other ways is as
well. So they are mature not just in body but in mind
earlier than boys. That's what Rabbi says based on a פסוק pasuk
but also, you know, based on things we can observe as well.
So now the גמרא Gemara says ואידך, v'idach,
what would Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar say? What would he do with
that פסוק? pasuk? ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדרבי שמעון בן לקיש, Hahu mibai
leh l'chid'Reish Lakish, he learns it to teach you a teaching of
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that פסוק. pasuk. דאמר ריש לקיש משום רבי
שמעון בן מנסיא, D'amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya, ויבן
ה׳ אלהים את הצלע אשר לקח מן האדם לאשה ויבאה אל האדם.
Vayiven Hashem Elokim et hatzela asher lakach min ha'adam l'ishah vayevi'eha el
ha'adam. God built the side or the rib that he took from
the man and he brought her to the man. מלמד שקילעה הקדוש
ברוך הוא לחוה והביאה אצל אדם הראשון. Melamed shekile'ah Hakadosh Baruch Hu
l'Chava v'hevi'ah eitzel Adam HaRishon.
God sort of like braided the hair of חוה Chava and brought
her to the first man. שכן, Shekein, where do you get that
from the פסוק? pasuk? בכרכי הים, B'charkei hayam, in the islands, קורין
לקליעתא בנייתא. korin l'kli'ata banyata.
They call braided hair בנייתא, banyata, the same word of ויבן. vayiven.
So ויבן vayiven means he braided her hair. Now exactly what we're
supposed to learn from that seems to be a message about like
you know about הכנסת כלה hachnasat kallah and about preparing the bride
and preparing the bride and groom for one another although clearly the
emphasis is on the bride in terms of, you know, for that
wedding day and for coming to each other under the חופה chuppah
and the מצוה mitzvah that there comes in preparing the bride and
groom but here again particular emphasis הכנסת כלה hachnasat kallah we normally
say on the bride. מהו כרכי הים?
Mahu charkei hayam?
בכרכי הים B'charkei hayam is like the islands.
It says ויבן את הצלע, vayiven et hatzela, so God braided the
צלע. tzela.
Right.
I mean it is a דרשה, drasha, so it means after he
made it into the אישה. ishah.
I don't know.
I don't know. Yes, Zilberberg. I don't know if the word. Oh,
that's interesting. The medical, yes.
In those days, I think, well at least if they lived longer
if they survived childbirth. Right. I mean, if you average it out,
I mean women died very, very frequently in childbirth. But I assume
right, if they survive the childbirth-ing period then I don't know, I
would guess they lived longer. We could check that out. Okay, yeah,
but that's a דרוש drush Rivka, I don't know what to say
about that.
Okay, so רב שמעון בן אלעזר Rav Shimon ben Elazar מאי טעמא,
mai ta'ama, what's the reason of רב שמעון בן אלעזר Rav Shimon
ben Elazar that says the ages are reversed?
אמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק Amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak
מתוך שתינוק מצוי בבית רבו mitoch shetinok matzui beveit rabo נכנסת בו
ערמומית תחילה. nichneset bo armumit techila. This is very interesting. This really
speaks to an awareness about
the implications about differences in the way boys and girls were treated
and the social realities because it says because boys go to school
more,
are found by their masters, by their teachers, then they become smarter
sooner. Sometimes differences
that could happen between boys and girls, like the famous גמרא Gemara
that speaks about women and ללמוד תורה lilmod Torah and can you
trust women with תורה Torah and so on, so sometimes those people
that make those arguments could be making claims about innate ability and
here actually it's not a claim about innate ability, it's a claim
about sometimes those differences are attributable to differences in society, that if
the boys are educated then they'll wind up, the girls aren't, then
as a general rule
they'll be smarter in things certainly at an earlier age than girls.
Now, of course, what if this boy per se isn't going to
school? So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says שתינוק
מצוי בבית רבו shetinok matzui beveit rabo ואפילו אין לו רב רגיל
להתחבר ולבא ומתפקח יותר. veafillu ein lo rav ragil lehitchaber uleva umitpake'ach
yoter.
Even if he doesn't have a teacher, but nevertheless he hangs around
the school kids more and therefore, because the boys are going to
school, he has friends who are going to school and even so,
even without having a teacher, being part of the favored class as
it were, the kids that are getting the education means that they
also mature quicker. So what? We don't פסקן pasken that way. No,
but what's fascinating is it's probably definitely true, right? I mean that
they, the boys got the education. I mean, I assume that still
young boys were still more wilder than thought, but
maybe not as much. I mean when boys had to start earning
a living at three years old and five years old which was
a reality, they maybe were forced to be a little bit more-
but wait- בעל בתיש. ba'al batish. That's true also. Anyway, but it
is, but what I think is particularly interesting
is the acknowledgement that that's not an innate difference, that that's based
on those societal realities.
It only takes a year for a girl to catch up to
the
boys' seven years of learning. There you go, there you go. It's
like people that didn't get a good Jewish education and they go
for a year in Israel and they've caught up to twelve years
of high school Jewish education.
Let's move on. Okay, but that's a different discussion. All right, anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they
raise the question: תוספת זמן כפני זמן או כלאחר זמן? Tosefet zman
kifnei zman o kelachar zman? Now, we sort of know the answer,
but this is saying: look, our משנה mishna discusses the year leading
up to בר בת מצוה bar bat mitzvah for this sort of
set issue about making vows and we check and see if someone
has הבנה. havana. What's the general rule for the year prior to
בר בת מצוה? bar bat mitzvah? Is it count like they're already
בר בת מצוה bar bat mitzvah or not? Now, of course, that
seems silly. The whole point of בר בת מצוה bar bat mitzvah
is that once you hit that age, then you're an adult, not
prior. But we've been seeing these discussions about the period before, thirty
days and that it's called the twelfth year, the thirteenth year, so
maybe it already counts. It's a funny question because then what would
be the significance of hitting that date itself? But let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. Does that period of the year leading up
count as the prior period or like you've already hit the period?
למאי הלכתא? Lemai hilchata? For what purposes? אי לנדרים, Ei lenedarim, if
it's like for vows, לאו כפני זמן דמי ולאו כלאחר זמן דמי.
lav kifnei zman dami velav kelachar zman dami. It's not like the
totally earlier and it's not like totally later, right? Totally earlier you
wouldn't bother checking the vows, it wouldn't do any good. Afterwards you
don't need to check the vows. So this twelfth year or thirteenth
year has a special in-between status. אלא, Ela, so the גמרא Gemara
says: לעונשין מאי? le'onshin mai?
For punishment, what? To be deserving of a court punishment. Now, it
seems that the גמרא, Gemara, like I said, of course you need
to be בר מצוה בת מצוה, bar mitzvah bat mitzvah, what's the
point of that day? So it seems like the גמרא Gemara knows
that that's true for issues like
having legal standing to enter into transactions, to marry, to give a
גט, get, areas of legal standing it understands is בר בת מצוה.
bar bat mitzvah. But it wants to know though is that that
might not necessarily mean that you can be punished by the court,
right? I mean that's true right now, right? You can do certain
things under age eighteen that are legally binding transactions, but you'll be,
the, your punishments are administered by a juvenile court and not by
an adult court. There's still a different question about what punishments you
deserve for transgression, for crimes, than whether you are an adult in
terms of the binding nature of your legal actions. So that seems
to be what the גמרא Gemara is saying. I get that בר
בת מצוה bar bat mitzvah is about adulthood for the legal nature
of your actions, but what about for being punished? And now, of
course, we would say that you should wait later, eighteen, twenty. The
גמרא Gemara is actually suggesting, right. that you go earlier, that maybe
the year before already you can be punished. So let's see what
it says. ומאי
הלכתא ve-mai hilchesa for what הלכה? halacha? אי לנדרים, i de-nedarim, if
it's for vows, I've already said that. So anyway, לעונשין מאי le-onshin
mai for punishment what? רב ורבי חנינא Rav ve-Rabbi Chanina דאמרי תרווייהו,
de-amri tarveihu, Rav and Rabbi Chanina say they both say, תוספת זמן
כלפני זמן, tosefet zman ki-lifnei zman, it's like before, it's early, it's
like before, the year before is like before, nothing happens till your
בר ובת מצוה. Bar and Bat Mitzvah. ורבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן
לוי ve-Rabbi Yochanan ve-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi דאמרי תרווייהו, de-amri tarveihu, and
Rabbi Yochanan and Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi say a surprising position that
no, even the year leading up is like it already happened and
you would be liable for punishment. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק וסימנך,
amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak ve-simanach, and this is the way you
remember it, וזאת לפנים בישראל, ve-zos lefanim be-Yisrael, this is early in
Israel, so it's like beforehand. But how does that tell you who's
saying it, who's saying what? So
רש"י Rashi says that וזאת ve-zos is feminine and רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina is the only name of these rabbis that sounds feminine because
it ends with like a קמץ ה, kamatz hei, not really a
קמץ ה kamatz hei but it sounds like it has חנינא. Chanina.
Okay, so רש"י Rashi also said that maybe the word בישראל be-Yisrael
has the letters of רב's Rav name in it. Anyway, somehow we're
supposed to know וזאת לפנים בישראל ve-zos lefanim be-Yisrael represents the position
of Rav and Rabbi Chanina which means that it is the earlier
period, that the year before is like the earlier period. Oh, I
see from Israel as opposed to no, Rabbi Yochanan is definitely from
Israel, Rabbi Shimon no, that's too bad, that didn't work. What?
Doesn't it mean
לפנים lefanim means like earlier?
Earlier, right, which is Rav and Rabbi Chanina's position, that the year
before is like the earlier period. But the question is how do
you know to attribute that לפנים lefanim to Rav and Rabbi Chanina?
Rather than how you know, you have the ב, be, what makes
that פסוק pasuk connected to them? So רש"י Rashi says because Rabbi
Chanina is a feminine sounding name. Okay, מתיב רב המנונא. meisiv Rav
Hamnuna. So רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna now asks and we'll see which
position he's
challenging. אחר זמן הזה, achar hazman hazeh, אף על פי שאמרו af
al pi she-amru איננו יודעים לשם מי נדרנו ולשם מי הקדשנו, einanu
yodim leshem mi nadarnu u-leshem mi hikdashnu, נדריהם נדר והקדשן הקדש. nidreihem
neder ve-hekdeshan hekdesh. So after this period, meaning twelve years and a
day, thirteen years and a day, even if they say we don't
know what we were talking about, tough luck, you're already an adult
and it counts regardless. הא תוך זמן כלפני זמן. ha toch zman
ki-lifnei zman. So you see, now again this is not about punishment.
So now the גמרא Gemara is interpreting the position more broadly. But
you see that they're considered after twelve years and a day, thirteen
years and a day they're considered full adults, there's no question of
asking what they were thinking. So that shows that prior to that
time, they're not yet full adults. Okay, now of course it's a
funny proof because we've already said vows is its own story. Anyway
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with that. אמר ליה רבא
אימא רישא. amar lei Rava eima reisha. No, you cannot infer it
from the implication of twelve years and a day implying that less
than that doesn't count. Because the beginning says קודם הזמן הזה kodem
hazman hazeh before the eleven and a day, אף על פי שאמרו
יודעים אנו לשם מי נדרנו ולשם מי הקדשנו, af al pi she-amru
yodim anu leshem mi nadarnu u-leshem mi hikdashnu, אין נדריהם נדר ואין
הקדשן הקדש, ein nidreihem neder ve-ein hekdeshan hekdesh, that before eleven and
a day nothing counts. So that says that only before eleven and
a day is it not meaningful, implying הא תוך זמן ha toch
zman during that one year eleven till twelve, כלאחר זמן ke-le-achar zman
it is meaningful. So so that you can't prove it. Sure, a
day after twelve years definitely counts. But that doesn't mean before is
nothing because a day before eleven years definitely doesn't count. The meaning
is an ambiguous period. So the גמרא Gemara says ולא היא, ve-lo
hi, that's not really a good response. רבא קטעי, Rava kotei, Rava
was making a mistake in what the proof was. הוא סבר רב
המנונא ממשנה יתירה קדייק. hu savar Rav Hamnuna mi-mishnah yesera kodayek. He
thought Rav Hamnuna was inferring not from the הלכה halacha but from
the fact that it you know
had an extra phrase in the משנה. Mishnah. As we pointed out
earlier in the דף, daf, so many of those phrases seem repeated.
So the extra phrase was telling you to infer from it why
do you have to go again and say twelve and a day
to infer that less than that doesn't count? That's what he thought
was a דיוק diyuk from an extra phrase.
ואידך משנה יתירה קדייק מרישא. ve-idach mishnah yesera kodayek me-reisha.
And if you want to be inferred from what you think is
a superfluous phrase that there's a hidden message, so why don't you
infer from the hidden phrase from the extra phrase at the beginning,
infer from the extra phrase at the beginning? ולא היא, ve-lo hi,
that wasn't his point.
His point was more substantive. רב המנונא מגופה דמתניתין קדייק. Rav Hamnuna
mi-gufa de-matnisin kodayek. He's pointing out from the law itself. הא לאחר
זמן היכי דמי. ha le-achar zman heichi dami. When the משנה Mishnah
says when you're twelve years and a day for a girl, we
don't care if you say you don't know what you're talking about,
right? Why? Presumably because then you're an adult. Okay, so
so what's the story when you're twelve years and a day we
don't care what you were talking we don't care what you said?
אי דלא אייתי שתי שערות, i de-la ayisi shtei searos, if you
do not have two pubic hairs because remember, and this is what
we're going to focus on for later today as well, it's not
just the age, it's the age plus the presence of two pubic
hairs that's the sign someone's an adult. We normally assume that when
you hit the age you have those pubic hairs but but if
it really mattered you'd check, okay, and you need both. So when
we say twelve years and a day at that stage talking about
a girl, adult, end of story, what's the story? If she doesn't
have pubic hairs, קטן הוא, katan hu, so he actually or she
whenever is a minor. Obviously that's not the case. אלא לאו דאייתי
שתי שערות, ela lav de-ayisi shtei searos, talking about you have the
pubic hairs, she has the pubic hairs. And then we say when
she's twelve and a day or he's thirteen and a day. day,
you don't bother checking their
hairs. וטעמא לאחר זמן הוא דגמיננא ליה מילתא, u'tama l'achar zman hu
d'gaminan leh milta, and the reason is is that because those two
hairs after the time, after 12 years and
a day or 13 years and a day, that's when the matters
are like complete, meaning that's when the hairs count after 12 years
and a day or 13 in a day. התו זמן כלפני זמן,
ha'to zman kilifnei zman, you see that earlier it's not meaningful. Now
again, what did any of that prove? Maybe this is just for
vows and we want to ask a different question, we wanted to
ask for punishment or we wanted to ask for things other than
vows. So it seems that the גמרא's Gemara proof is the following,
meaning and here's an important, a critical question, I mean it doesn't
seem like a big deal but there are נפקא מינות nafka minos
in this, and this is one of them, about how we think
of these two criteria of 12 years and a day and two
pubic hairs or 13 years and a day and two pubic hairs.
It's always an interesting question when you have two criteria, ask yourself
what's the relationship between them. Are they independent criteria? You need both
things, you need physical maturity and you need age, two separate things.
Or are they fundamentally one criteria and one is sort of needed
to make the other one count? And that seems to be what
this גמרא's Gemara saying. Really it's a question of pubic hair. Okay,
but pubic hairs when they come earlier at an early age are
not considered to be pubic hairs. The גמרא, Gemara, that sounds weird,
but the גמרא Gemara is actually going to say in a minute
some type of a thing like that. Maybe it's random hair growing,
maybe it's not going to stay that way, maybe it's not a
full sign of maturity. Only when it comes when you're a certain
age is it seen as a sign of maturity. But the age
is to contextualize and give meaning to what those those pubic hairs
mean. That's one way of understanding how those two combine. So that
seems to be the גמרא's Gemara point. Look, even in the issue
of vows, we consider 12 years and a day, 13 years and
a day to be you're done. Now you're done with the pubic
hairs. So that proves that those pubic hairs don't have meaning earlier.
Because if we're talking with pubic hairs and now you've hit 12
and a day, 13 and a day, it means that if you
had them earlier they would be meaningless. So you see the period
beforehand is meaningless in defining the significance of the pubic hair. That's
what the גמרא Gemara says, assuming that those are sort of like,
you know, linked criteria. And but of course if that's true, then
you really, you know, it undermines the way the גמרא Gemara framed
the question because the גמרא Gemara framed the question like maybe there
are different standards for different הלכות, halachos, one thing's for vows, I
tried to say another thing for legal actions, a third thing for
an age to be punished, עונשים, onshim, okay? And the גמרא's Gemara
answer is basically no, no, no, it's all just about whether you're
physically mature and whether those pubic hairs mean something. So if it
means something for one category, it means something for all the categories.
Okay, so that's how the גמרא's Gemara trying to prove it from
the case of vows. Let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues. ועוד
מותיב רב זירא. v'od maseiv Rav Zeira. רב זירא Rav Zeira also
asks. Basically all these are going to be challenging the position you
know that we reject, which is that the year before counts. The
year before doesn't count except for vows, it only really becomes an
adult at בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah or בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. So
here's the challenge. איש כי יפלי לנדור נדר. ish ki yafli lindor
neder. If a man who יפלי yafli enunciates, that's where the word
of מופלא mufla means, to enunciate, to do a verbal act that
causes some type of a status change, to make a vow. מה
תלמוד לומר איש? mah talmud lomar ish? Why did it say a
man? לרבות בן י"ג שנה ויום אחד שאף על פי שאינו יודע
להפליא נדרו קיים. l'rabos ben thalosh esrei shana v'yom echad she'af al
pi she'eino yodea l'hafli nidro kayam. To tell you that once you're
a man by boy,
13 and a day, then it's a good vow even if you
say you don't know what you're talking about. Okay, so היכי דמי?
heichi dami? Again it's the same basic הלכה. halacha. That it's definitely
a good vow and there's no question about it once you're an
adult, once you're 13 and a day. What's the case? אי דלא
אייתי שתי שערות? ei d'lo aiti shtei saarot? It's basically just repeating
the same point. If you don't yet have the two hairs prior,
you know, at that age of 13, קטן הוא. katan hu. Then
who cares that you're 13? אלא לאו דאייתי שתי שערות? ela lav
d'aiti shtei saarot? It must be you have the two hairs. וטעמא,
v'tama, and even with the two hairs we're saying, the only reason
you're considered an adult is דבן י"ג שנה ויום אחד הוא d'ben
thalosh esrei shana v'yom echad hu דהוה ליה איש d'hava leh ish
because you're 13 and a day and therefore you're considered a man.
Today I am a man. התו זמן כלפני זמן. ha'to zman kilifnei
zman. So you see beforehand it doesn't count, it's like the period
before it has no status. תיובתא. tiyuvta. That is an absolute contradiction.
So again, quite funny, I think, that the גמרא Gemara starts by
saying we understand vows are different, we want to know about עונשים,
onshim, punishments. And at the end it brings a proof from the
world of vows. It says, look, since you see that's when pubic
hairs matter, 13 and a day, 12 and a day, clearly any
status of those hairs earlier would be meaningless for any הלכה, halacha,
end of discussion. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב
נחמן כתנאי. amar Rav Nachman k'tannai. So said רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
this really is a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. Here's the ברייתא. braisa. בן ט' שנים שהביא ב' שערות.
ben tesha shanim shehevi shtei saarot. And here you see the idea
about the focus on whether the what those the hairs mean, not
just the age as an independent criteria. Nine years old that brings
up that has two
hairs. שומא. shuma. Anything from nine years and earlier those pubic hairs
are considered שומא shuma like some type of like fattiness, meaning it's
growing from some, from something else. going on in your skin and
it is not related to pubic hairs and they cannot be read
as the sign of puberty. Okay, that's if it's under nine years.
Let me let me where are we? מבן ט' ועד בן י"ב
שנה, Mi-ben tet v'ad ben yud-bet shana, if it's twelve, if it's
nine and a day until the end of your twelfth year, until
twelve years, this is about a girl, ויום אחד, v'yom echad, שומא,
shuma, then still until you hit בת מצוה, bat mitzvah, twelve years
and a day, it's this like, you know, it's like this what
I get I'm searching for a good English word for שומא, shuma,
whatever it is, it's a non-pubic hair, it's some type of a
random hair and it's not meaningful. Okay, now okay, so then why
do you say this period of nine to twelve if it's the
same as before? Because actually surprisingly there's a position of רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר סימן,
Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehuda omer siman, no that is a sign of
puberty. He actually says that a pubic hair that develops after nine
years old already counts as a sign of puberty. That's a pretty
shocking idea. According to him you could be an adult earlier. Now
the גמרא Gemara is going to qualify it but that seems to
be what he is saying.
Yes, is this perhaps related to the idea of a boy who
has sex?
Right, it seems to be. Right, although of course
what right
of course it's a little strange because it should have said the
language here is strange. It said מבן ט' ועד בן י"ב, mi-ben
tet v'ad ben yud-bet, it's true and it sounds like it's a
boy because it also emphasizes nine, but then it says ועד י"ב
שנה ויום אחד. v'ad yud-bet shana v'yom echad. It should have really
said ועד י"ג שנה. v'ad yud-gimel shana. You know what I mean?
Well actually that's the גמרא's Gemara דיוק. diyuk. Okay so let's hold
off. You're right, you're right. Okay, so let's take a look. So
it does sound like it's talking about a boy. But but interestingly,
and yes, maybe it is because nine years old we said before
is considered an act of sex, but interestingly it focuses on the
time frame from nine to twelve. Okay, and there you have רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosei saying, ah, that already he could be an adult
if he has pubic hair. Okay, but now you have the חכמים's
Chachamim position. And then it says where are we? בן י"ג שנה
ויום אחד, ben yud-gimel shana v'yom echad, thirteen and a day, דברי
הכל סימן, divrei hakol siman, everybody says it counts as a sign
of puberty. So it's very strange. Let's bracket רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehuda for a minute. It says nine and twelve
it doesn't count, between nine and twelve, and at thirteen it definitely
counts. Well we didn't discuss between twelve and thirteen, right? So what's
going on there? So that's what the גמרא Gemara picks up. Let's
put רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehuda aside. Why does
the first part say between nine and twelve and then the next
part say at thirteen
it's a sign of maturity? So the גמרא Gemara says like this
הא גופא קשיא, ha gufa kashya, this is an internal contradiction. אמרת
מבן ט' ועד י"ב שנה ויום אחד שומא, amarta mi-ben tet v'ad
yud-bet shana v'yom echad shuma,
you said from nine to twelve it's only like a false hair,
it doesn't count. הא י"ג שנה גופא, ha yud-gimel shana gufa, the
thirteenth year itself, from twelve to thirteen assuming we're talking about a
boy,
גופא
סימן, gufa siman, it would count because you said from nine to
twelve so and then you said and then I skipped a והדר
תני, v'hadar tani, and then you said בן י"ג שנה ויום אחד
סימן, ben yud-gimel shana v'yom echad siman, no from thirteen and a
day is when it counts. עד י"ג שנה גופא שומא, ad yud-gimel
shana gufa shuma, the thirteenth year itself, the year leading up, שומא,
shuma, it's a meaningless hair. So מאי לאו תנאי היא, mai lav
tana-hi, it must be that this is really two different opinions. That's
actually not a bad read of the ברייתא, baraita, right? It says
from nine to twelve it doesn't count. Sounds like from twelve it
does. And then the last opinion said by thirteen everybody agrees it
counts. It sounds like there's this period between twelve and thirteen where
some people say it counts and some people say it doesn't. So
it says that sounds like it's a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. דמר סבר תוספת זמן כזמן, d'mar savar tosfot zman k'zman,
some say that year leading up is like you're already thirteen and
it counts, ומר סבר תוספת זמן כלפני זמן, u'mar savar tosfot zman
k'lifnei zman, no only once you hit thirteen, not the year prior.
So it sounds like what we're debating is really two opinions in
this in this ברייתא. baraita. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo,
no, not necessarily. I could tell you דכולי עלמא תוספת זמן כלפני
זמן, d'kulei alma tosfot zman k'lifnei zman, everybody says it's like the
earlier
period. אידי ואידי בתינוקת, idi v'idi b'tinokes, and they're both but you
know what? They're talking about not boys, they're talking about girls. And
so רישא רבי, reisha Rebbi, so the first set says from nine
to twelve it doesn't count, at the age of twelve it does
count, that's because we're talking about a girl. So now how come
the end said at thirteen it counts? סיפא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר,
seifa Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar, because remember we said a minute ago
that's the position of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar
that by girls it goes by thirteen. So you're right, there's an
opinion here that says by twelve it counts and an opinion says
by thirteen it counts. But it's not because we count the year
prior. It's because we're talking about the debate of do girls go
by twelve or do girls go by thirteen. Now David going back
to what you said that makes this ברייתא baraita very strange that
it's talking about girls and gives significance to the age of nine.
We never spoke about the age of nine being significant to girls
before this. But that's the way the first גמרא Gemara reads it.
איבעית אימא, iba'it eima, and if you want you could say which
should be obvious what the next possible possibility is, הא והא בתינוק,
ha v'ha b'tinok, we're talking about boys. One says twelve, one says
thirteen. Right? So it could be we're talking about girls and we're
debating do girls go by twelve or thirteen? Could be we're talking
about boys, do boys go by twelve or thirteen? רישא רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר, reisha Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar, the beginning that says twelve,
that's רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar. סיפא, seifa, the
end that says thirteen is רבי. Rebbi. Okay, but it's not about
a question of does the year before count or not? It's about
what age do you go by for boys? What age do you
go by for girls? איבעית אימא הא והא רבי, iba'it eima ha
v'ha Rebbi, maybe it's both. הא בתינוק הא בתינוקת. Ha bitinok ha
bitinokes. Maybe first when we said 12, we were talking about a
girl. Then when the end of the ברייתא Baraisa said 13, we
were talking about a boy. So it's not that there's an argument,
it's just first we're talking about a girl, then we're talking about
a boy. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eima, and of course the last
possibility: הא כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Ha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. הא
בתינוק הא בתינוקת, Ha bitinok ha bitinokes, except flip it. The beginning
when it says 12 was talking about a boy, the end when
it says 13 was talking about a girl. So you are right,
you identified in this ברייתא Baraisa an opinion that says 12, an
opinion that says 13. But there's so many other things it could
be about, rather than the question of does the year before count
or not? Maybe it's a question of one is a boy and
one is a girl? Maybe it's a debate when you go by
for boys? Maybe it's a debate when you go by for girls?
It doesn't prove your issue of whether the year before counts or
not. Okay, so we cannot prove it from that. So now the
גמרא Gemara goes on. רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר סימן. Rabbi Yosei
bar Yehuda omer siman. So now let's talk at the statement of
רבי יוסי בר יהודה, Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda, which is a shocking
one, that even from the age of nine up, maybe by a
boy, maybe by a girl, but the age of nine up, a
pubic hair counts and this person, and this child could be an
adult. Would we really say that like a nine-year-old can be an
adult? So the גמרא Gemara immediately qualifies it. אמר רב קריספידא, Amar
Rav Krispida, says רב קריספידא, Rav Krispida, interesting word, he is an
אמורא Amora that appears a good number of times in ש"ס. Shas.
Does anybody know what the Aramaic word קריספידא Krispida means? It was
in the תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos just a parsha ago, a parsha
or two ago. Krisp... no? If you look at the אונקלוס Onkelos
on עשו לכם ציצית, Asu lachem tzitzis, the Aramaic of ציצית tzitzis
is כרוספדא. krispida. Did you know that? Very... how often do you
need to say the word ציצית tzitzis in Aramaic?
So, I believe he did the אונקלוס Onkelos at the end of
שלח. Shlach. עשו להם ציצית, Asu lahem tzitzis, מללין
עם בני ישראל ותימא להון ויעבדון להון כרוספדין
Malilin im bnei Yisrael v'teima
lahon v'ya'avdun lahon krispedin על כנפי בגדיהם al kanfei vigdeihem ויתנון על
כרוספדא v'yitnun al krispeda דכנפא פתיל דתכלת. d'kanfa psil d'techeiles. Okay, so
said Rabbi ציצית, Tzitzis, said רב קריספידא, Rav Krispida, בריה דרב יהודה,
breih d'Rav Yehuda, בריה דרב שבתי, breih d'Rav Shabsai, והוא שעודן בו.
v'hu she'odan bo. When does a pubic hair at the age of
nine count? It doesn't mean it counts at nine years old. Again,
here we really see the idea of independent criteria. He says, you
got the hair when you were nine and now it stayed on
and now you're בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, now you're 13. Then that
hair counts. Now you say, oh obviously, you're 13 and you have
a pubic hair. But no, remember, if the age is playing a
function not as an independent criteria, but to bring the meaning to
indicate whether it counts as a pubic hair or not, then you
would say maybe it's only hair that grows after you hit that
age. But if it was there at an earlier age, we've already
identified it as meaningless hair, and therefore it's not meaningful even if
it's on you after the age of בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. So
he's explaining רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda to say
you can't be בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah at nine. What he's saying
it is that age is an independent criteria. So if you hit
בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah and you have a pubic hair, even if
the pubic hair grew earlier, even if it grew as early as
the age of nine, then they combine and they make you בר
מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. Earlier than nine, it wouldn't be a pubic hair.
But he doesn't say that the age functions to define it, age
is a separate criteria and the hair can actually become from an
earlier time. That's how we read it, very interesting. Okay. והוא שעודן
בו, V'hu she'odan bo, when they're still on you. תניא נמי הכי,
Tanya nami hachi, we taught so too, בן תשע שנים ויום אחד
שהביא שתי שערות Ben tesha shanim v'yom echad sheheivi shtei se'aros שומא,
shuma, if he has these two hairs at nine years old, it's
meaningless. מבן תשע ועד שתים עשרה שנה ויום אחד ועודן בו, Miben
tesha v'ad shteim esrei shana v'yom echad v'odan bo, if it was
from nine to twelve and they're still on him now that he's
בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah aged, or she, nonetheless שומא, shuma, it's meaningless.
ורבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר סימן, V'Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda omer siman,
no, it counts. So now that is quite fascinating, because now we
find out another fascinating הלכה, halacha, because if we don't rule like
רבי יוסי בר יהודה, Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda, it means that you
have a בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah boy, or a בת מצוה Bas
Mitzvah girl, they're really not an adult unless this hair grew after
they hit בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. So the actual, if it was
on from beforehand, it's not yet considered a pubic hair, right? It's
only רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda that said it
could be considered a pubic hair that grew early. We're saying no,
the age is what defines it, now we're saying that means that
it grew after you hit that age. Right? So that would mean
that almost no boy or girl is ever בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah
on their day of בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. Because what's the likelihood
that the hair actually grew on that day? Okay, I don't know,
maybe you could say that if they already had hair growing, and
hair is always growing, so it grew a little bit more, I'm
not sure if that would count. Right? But we, that would be
a very strange conclusion, but actually the רמב"ם Rambam rules that way.
The רמב"ם Rambam says, hair that grew prior to בר מצוה Bar
Mitzvah doesn't count, it only counts if it grew after בר מצוה.
Bar Mitzvah. So based on that, the likelihood that on the age,
on the
day of בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, somebody is actually a בר מצוה
Bar Mitzvah or בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah would be... and we normally
don't say that. So I don't know exactly how we reconcile rejecting
רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda with our assumption, because
we're about to see the question about when it really matters, you
have to make sure that he has pubic hairs, which is why,
for example, we don't have בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah boys do like
פרשת זכור, Parshas Zachor, because you know that's a מצוה דאורייתא, mitzvah
d'oraisa, and we say you have to know for certain that you're
a בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. and your age is not enough of
a proof. But if basically, let's say, you know, he's got, let's
say, facial hair, the גמרא Gemara says that facial hair is an
indication that there's also pubic hair, then it's okay. Okay, but why
do we say, well, who knows, maybe it didn't, maybe if today's
her בר מצוה bar mitzvah they didn't grow today, maybe it was
only from before. So to some degree we don't really pay attention
to this, but the conclusions would be pretty significant about whether again
you make this idea of age and the pubic hair as independent
criteria or linked criteria. So now, so something to think about. Now
we go on to talk about exactly this issue about what do
we assume when you hit that age without knowing the pubic hair.
So let's take a look. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, first we have
to wrap up the previous
discussion, והלכתא, v'hilchasa, תוך זמן כלפני זמן, toch zman kilfnei zman, that,
and we sort of knew that, that the year leading up is
like the year prior, you have to hit בר מצוה bar mitzvah
for it to be meaningful. ורב שמואל בר זוטרא מתני לה להא
שמעתא דרבא בהאי לישנא. v'Rav Shmuel bar Zutra masni lah l'ha shma'ata
d'Rava b'hai lishna. Now Rav Shmuel bar Zutra teaches the teaching of
Rava that the year before doesn't count, not based on like in
the context of the earlier discussion, based on the following
discussion. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, קטנה כל י"ב שנה ממאנת והולכת, מכאן
ואילך אינה ממאנת ואינה חולצת. ketana kol yud-beiz shana memanes v'holeches, mikan
v'eilach eina memanes v'eina choletzes. Okay, so now we're going to get
into, this is going to lead us into a discussion about when
do we assume the presence of pubic hairs or not, but it's
going to also teach us at least at the first stage that
the year leading up doesn't count. Now, it leads to two הלכות
halachos you have to know, they don't coincide but they're dealt with
parallel because they're, you're able to illustrate the הלכה halacha based on
that.
מיאון Meeun is refusal. A girl, an underage girl could be married
off by her father as we know, and it's binding and she
can't do anything about it. The only way she can get out
of it is by a גט get from her husband. However, because
there were
socioeconomic reasons that underage girls had to be married off, the rabbis
instituted that even when there was no living father, the father was
dead, the mother and brothers could also arrange a marriage, a quasi-binding
marriage for the underage girl. Okay, and the fact that, you know,
the rabbis felt a need to create that institution shows that there
was a real socioeconomic need for that at the time. Again, it
doesn't mean like we said before that they started actually living together
and having sex at a young age, but there was a need
for creating that, you know, for marrying the girls off. So that's
a rabbinic institution. Now, because it's only rabbinic, the rabbis said that
until the girl hits בת מצוה, bas mitzvah, she can refuse. If
she does a verbal refusal, מיאון, meeun, and the marriage is unbinding.
Once however she hits בת מצוה bas mitzvah and then, then it's
too late and she cannot do מיאון. meeun. So for the הלכה
halacha of מיאון, meeun, it's important to establish that she's still a
minor. It's only valid, it's interesting, it's one of the few הלכות
halachos which is valid only as a minor. So that's right, everything
else, nothing is valid as a minor. Here it's only valid as
a minor.
And then only if the mother or brother
married her off, right, and
not the father.
If the father, right, then she has no recourse. Right, then she's
stuck. So that's the הלכה halacha of מיאון meeun which is which
is used because it's an interesting הלכה halacha which is valid only
as a minor. Then in a totally different case, not related to
this case, if a, if a woman's husband died, and she could
be underage because she was married by her father, her husband died,
then the living brother would do יבום. yibum. Now, you cannot do,
יבום yibum is a discussion, but certainly you cannot do חליצה chalitza
if the, if the girl is a minor. So there, if you
wanted to do חליצה, chalitza, not in the same case, because that
would, יבום yibum would only be with a biblically binding marriage, but
if you wanted to do חליצה, chalitza, you would have to know
that she's definitely an adult. So these are two cases to illustrate
the question of are you an adult, are you a minor? מיאון
Meeun only works for a minor, חליצה chalitza only works for an
adult. Okay,
separate scenarios but two cases to illustrate. So let's see what רבא
Rava says. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, קטנה כל י"ב שנה ממאנת והולכת.
ketana kol yud-beiz shana memanes v'holeches. A young girl, her entire 12th
year, until she hits 12 years and a day, she could do
מיאון. meeun. She doesn't have to worry, she's definitely a minor. מכאן
ואילך אינה ממאנת ואינה חולצת. mikan v'eilach eina memanes v'eina choletzes. Once
she's 12 years and a day, she can't do מיאון meeun because
she might be an adult. She can't do חליצה, chalitza, she might
be a minor. Now what does that mean she might be an
adult she might be a minor, she's already 12 years and a
day? What's the question? Pubic hair. Pubic hair. So since at that
period we don't know if she has pubic hair or not, you
might be an adult, you might be a minor. Okay, so that,
from there you see אלמא, alma, so the גמרא Gemara says one
second, האי גופא קשיא, hai gufa kashya, this is contradictory. Why? אמרת
אינה ממאנת, amarta eina memanes, you said that she can't do מיאון
meeun after 12 years and a day. אלמא גדולה היא, alma gedola
hi, it means you're assuming she's an adult. אי גדולה היא תחלוץ,
ei gedola hi tachlotz, if she's an adult, let her do חליצה.
chalitza. So the obvious answer here is that we don't know. וכי
תימא מספקא ליה, v'ki seima mesafka lei, we have a doubt 12
years and a day whether to treat you as an adult or
a minor, we don't know if you have pubic hair or not.
ומי מספקא ליה, u'mi mesafka lei, since when does רבא Rava have
a
doubt? והאמר רבא, v'ha'amar Rava, קטנה שהגיעה לכלל שנותיה, ketana shehigia lichlal
shnoseha, once a minor girl reaches her age, 12 years and a
day, אינה צריכה בדיקה, eina tzricha bdika, you don't need to check.
חזקה הביאה סימנים, chazaka hevia simanim, you can assume she's had her
pubic hairs. Now again, that is quite bizarre assuming what we've just
said that the hairs have to grow only once you hit the
Bat Mitzvah, right? But be that as it may, we'll bracket that.
This is a very important הלכה halacha for for all purposes of
Bar and Bat Mitzvah that it's called חזקה דרבא. chazaka de-Rava. Rava's
חזקה, chazaka, which is the יסוד, yesod, the assumption that when you
hit the 12 years and a day, 13 years and a day,
you also have the pubic hairs, and we let you do various
functions that would require being Bar or Bat Mitzvah. Now again, to
tell you what I said before, we only say חזקה דרבא chazaka
de-Rava by דרבנן, miderabbanan, by rabbinic laws. By דאורייתא de-oraita laws, we
don't rely on the חזקה, chazaka, we need either to see the
facial hairs which is a proof of pubic hairs by a boy,
or to actually know the pubic hairs, but it's a biblical. But
for rabbinic things, we apply חזקה דרבא chazaka de-Rava and we assume
once you hit the age, you have the pubic hairs. So the
גמרא Gemara says, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't know that difference yet
between rabbinic and biblical. So the גמרא Gemara says: Look, Rava says
we assume pubic hairs by that age, so why does he not
know, why does he put you in this middle status when you're
12 years and a day? So the גמרא Gemara says, let's see
what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. חזקה
דהביאה סימנים. chazaka de-hevia simanim. הני מילי בסתם. hani mili bestam. So
you know what? True. That's like in a normal case we would
assume you have the pubic hairs. So why can't she do חליצה?
chalitza? אבל הכא דבדקו ולא אשכחו
לה. aval hacha debadku velo ashkechu lah. But here they've actually checked
and they saw she didn't have pubic hairs, so then obviously we
can't assume she's an adult. So why is this girl who's 12
years and a day have to be concerned maybe she's a minor
maybe she's an adult? Well because there are no pubic hairs. Okay.
So let that be a proof she's definitely a
minor. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי תמאן. ei hachi teman.
So then do מיאון. mi'un. If there's no pubic hairs and you
know that for a fact then you're a minor and do מיאון.
mi'un. Actually that's a good way to remember minor and מיאון. mi'un.
Very good סימן siman there. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says no.
חוששין שמא נשרו. choshshin shema nashru. Even if you didn't find it
we would be concerned that maybe they were there and they fell
off. Okay. So basically the גמרא's Gemara saying when does Rava have
a doubt? When you're 12 years and a day not if you
didn't look. If you didn't look you assume pubic hairs. If you
look and there were no pubic hairs then we don't know. Maybe
they were there and you're and they fell out, you're an adult.
Maybe they were never there and you're a minor. So when you
don't see them that's when you have a doubtful status.
And they go that morning and they already fell out.
Basically. So if you if you incorporate what we said before, that's
true. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר חוששין. hani-cha leman
de-amar choshshin. That's fine according to the opinion that says if you
don't see we're concerned they fell out. אלא למאן דאמר אין חוששין.
ela leman de-amar ein choshshin. If you say we're not concerned that
they fell out מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemimar? What can you
say? דאתמר de-itmar because that was another debate. Right? So one debate
is before the time like the time or not. That we've put
to rest. Before the time is not like the time. That's implicit
by the way in this idea about מיאון mi'un and חליצה. chalitza.
It said until 12 years and a day nothing is meaningful. So
you see before the time is not meaningful. That was one question.
Then we have another question about pubic hairs that grew earlier. Now
we've got a question about what do you assume if you didn't
see pubic
hairs. And Rava's statement you assume they're there. Now we have another
question which is if you saw that there were no pubic hairs
can you go by what you didn't see or maybe you have
to assume that they were there and they fell out? And that's
also debated. דאתמר de-itmar was taught. רב פפא, Rav Pappa, some say
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, אמר אין חוששין. amar ein choshshin. If you
don't see them you don't have to worry about them. שמא נשרו.
shema nashru. You don't have to worry that they were there and
fell out. רב פפי אמר חוששין. Rav Pappi amar choshshin. Rav Pappi
says you are concerned that they might have been there. So even
when you see nothing you say maybe she's an adult. So the
גמרא Gemara said ah, so according to that since there's a debate,
Rava said during this time of 12 and a day it's a
doubt. Now the גמרא Gemara wants to say what's the doubt? If
you didn't check then according to Rava you should assume she's an
adult you should assume pubic hairs. If you did check, so there
are some that say, so it's true there's one opinion that says
you checked and there's still a doubt what the status is. There's
another the opinion says when you checked there's no doubt you go
on not seeing the hairs and she's a minor. So if you
take those various opinions how do you have a doubt? Without checking
she assumes she's definitely adult. With checking and no hairs you assume
she's definitely a minor. What's the case that you could be in
doubt of? So the גמרא Gemara says הני מילי לעניין חליצה. hani
mili le'inyan chalitza.
That's true. That's when it comes to for חליצה. chalitza. אבל לעניין
מיאון חוששין. aval le'inyan mi'un choshshin. For מיאון mi'un you are concerned.
What does that mean? It means you don't see hairs so you
don't you don't think maybe there's hair maybe she could do חליצה.
chalitza. That's pretty obvious. Obviously you're not going to assume maybe there's
hair to allow her to do חליצה, chalitza, you would need evidence
to prove that she was an adult if you didn't see hair.
So when it says you're not concerned it means that you're not
concerned to allow her to do חליצה. chalitza. But it doesn't mean
you can assume she's definitely a minor. You also wouldn't allow her
to do מיאון. mi'un. Okay? So basically it means you don't see
anything you really don't know what the story is. So the גמרא
Gemara says okay but then that's not an interesting position. מכלל דמאן
דאמר חוששין. michlal deman de-amar choshshin. That means the person that says
that without a hair you're concerned there was a hair would mean
not just you're concerned there was a hair would actually mean according
to the way you're framing it you can assume there was a
hair. the hair. חליצה? chalitzah? And would allow you to do חליצה?
chalitzah? וחוששין בעלמא קאמר, V'chosheshin b'alma ka'amar, it says whether you're concerned,
meaning, right, if the one opinion says you're concerned, by concerned it
means we don't know how to we're going to be strict either
way. So the one that says you're not concerned, doesn't mean you're
strict either way, means you definitely can assume that there was no
hair. So we're back to the question: what's the area of doubt?
אלא לעולם דלא בדקה. Ella l'olam d'lo badka. Fine, fine, fine. Forget
the case that she checked. If you checked, maybe you could go
by the lack of a hair and assume definitely minor. Forget checking.
So what's the case that רבא Rava has a doubt? That you
didn't check. Now what about the fact that רבא Rava says you
can assume there is a hair when you hairs when you didn't
check? אלא לעולם דלא בדקה, Ella l'olam d'lo badka, ולעניין חליצה חיישינן.
ul'inyan chalitzah chayshinan. And it's true רבא Rava says you could assume
there's hair, but you know what? Not 100%. It means that really
you can assume there's hairs, it means you have to be concerned
there might be hairs. Okay? So what we're going to reframe what
רבא Rava said. רבא Rava said when you hit בר ובת מצווה
bar v'bas mitzvah we can assume hairs, it really means we think
there might be hairs, which means really that you have to be
strict both ways. Don't do חליצה chalitzah because maybe there aren't hairs.
Don't do מיאון mi'un maybe there are hairs. והכי קאמר רבא חזקה
למיאון. V'hachi ka'amar Rava chazakah l'mi'un. When did רבא Rava say you
assume they were hairs? To tell you don't do מיאון, mi'un, which
doesn't really mean חזקה, chazakah, it just means there might be hairs,
so don't do מיאון. mi'un. אבל לחליצה בעי בדיקה. Aval l'chalitzah ba'ei
bdikah. For חליצה, chalitzah, that's when you would need בדיקה. bdikah. Now
the way I just read it is that really רבא, Rava, it's
a complete revamping of רבא. Rava. רבא Rava is not saying twelve
years and a day we assume hairs. He's saying twelve years and
a day maybe it's true. And because of maybe, don't do חליצה,
chalitzah, don't do מיאון. mi'un. Right? Absolute. So there's no longer a
חזקה דרבא. chazakah d'Rava. He's just saying you have a doubt. But
that's not the phrase the גמרא Gemara uses. The גמרא Gemara says
when it comes to מיאון mi'un then it's a חזקה, chazakah, which
means that, which seems to mean that, that actually if she did
מיאון mi'un at this age it's definitely not good. Not possibly not
good, definitely not good. For מיאון mi'un it's a חזקה. chazakah. Okay,
now why would we say that difference? So this leads to what
I was telling you at the beginning, that this idea of חזקה
דרבא chazakah d'Rava you can assume pubic hairs for rabbinic laws and
not for biblical laws. So חליצה chalitzah is a biblical law, you
can't assume pubic hairs, I'm sorry, you can't do a חליצה. chalitzah.
And if you did it, you know, maybe it was good, but
we're not going to say it was good. That's a biblical law.
For מיאון, mi'un, which is a rabbinic institution, there we're going to
go by the חזקה. chazakah. And we're going to say if you
had the two pubic hairs, we're not going to say if you
hit בת מצווה bat mitzvah we're not going to say maybe it
was good maybe it wasn't good, we're going to say we're definitely
going to assume pubic hairs for rabbinic laws. Okay? So this is
one way of reading the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is just
no חזקה, chazakah, it's just a ספק. safek. Okay? But the other
way is it is a חזקה. chazakah. It works for something like
מיאון mi'un which is a rabbinic law, it doesn't work for something
like חליצה chalitzah which is a biblical law. And that has all
very broad ramifications like I said about, you know, primarily for boys
because girls I guess the case would be for like מגילת אסתר
Megillat Esther or other types of things or counting for זימון, zimmun,
not the two cases, but basically that for all things that are
rabbinic, which is like 98% of our ritual life, right? דאוונען davening
and קריאת התורה krias haTorah and מגילת אסתר Megillat Esther and all
those things are all rabbinic. Right? The only things that really are
דאורייתא d'Oraisa is like פרשת זכור parshas zachor and
תקיעת שופר. tkiyas shofar. But anyway, maybe דאוונען davening on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. Anyway, so almost all of our ritual synagogue life is
all rabbinic. There you assume בר ובת מצווה, bar v'bas mitzvah, you
don't have to worry about the pubic hairs. זימון zimmun is it's
all rabbinic, right? All those things. Right. So anyway, those things that
you don't have to worry, but you can assume pubic hairs once
they hit בר ובת מצווה. bar v'bas mitzvah. The only case you
can't rely on רבא Rava is for דאורייתא d'Oraisa laws. Okay? So
that's the one way of reading this conclusion, not that it's just
a חשש, chashash, but a difference between דרבנן d'rabbanan and דאורייתא. d'Oraisa.
Let's take a look. They put on תפילין. tefillin.
Yeah, but they start doing that even before בר מצווה, bar mitzvah,
right? And the question is whether they get credit up in sky
for that? I
don't know. They make ברכות brachos anyway הכי נמי. hachi nami. Yeah.
So anyway, alright. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
What they could be מוציא motzi somebody with their ברכה bracha but
that's ברכות brachos is rabbinic anyway. Alright. So let's take a look.
אמר רב דימי מנהרדעא, Amar Rav Dimi mi-Neharde'a, says רב דימי מנהרדעא,
Rav Dimi mi-Neharde'a, הלכתא חוששין שמא נשרו. hilchata chosheshin shema nashru. We're
concerned that they fell out. Meaning going back to the earlier discussion,
if you looked and saw that there wasn't hairs, that's not enough
of evidence that she's a minor. Okay? Which sort of really reinforces
the point. Once she's hit בת מצווה bat mitzvah or a boy
בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, we're really concerned that there are pubic hairs
if you didn't see it, and you know what? Even if you
saw it wasn't there, you're concerned that there were pubic hairs. Okay?
חוששין שמא נשרו. Chosheshin shema nashru. והני מילי היכא דקידשה בתוך זמן,
V'hani mili haycha d'kidsah b'toch zman, but now again we're going to
get to a דרבנן d'rabbanan דאורייתא d'Oraisa difference. That's when let's say
he married her during the period, meaning it was a rabbinic marriage
with the brothers not with the father. קידשה בתוך זמן ובא לאחר
זמן. Kidsah b'toch zman u'ba l'achar zman. And then they had sex
afterwards. Meaning and the fact that they had sex afterwards, if they
stayed married even though it began as a rabbinic marriage, as they're
having sex once she became an adult, then that constitutes. due to
the act of marriage and then they're biblically married. So the question
here now is, okay, they were married before she was בת מצוה.
Bat Mitzvah. They had sex after בת מצוה. Bat Mitzvah. Now she
says I am still a minor and I want to do מיאון.
miun. And look, I don't have pubic hairs. Then we're saying I'm
sorry, you know, the absence of pubic hairs is not good enough
because here you might because you've already had sex and that might
if you had the pubic hairs and you were an adult, then
you're biblically married. So we cannot assume even in the absence once
you're at the right age, we can't assume you're a minor to
let you do מיאון miun because this might be a biblical issue
right now, you might biblically be married. So then we cannot go
by it.
אדיבא ועיקרא לא, Adeiva ve'ikara lo, let's say that they haven't had
sex yet after she hit בת מצוה. Bat Mitzvah. So now, yes
she is 12 years and a day, but still her marriage to
this guy is only rabbinic because they haven't had sex after בת
מצוה. Bat Mitzvah. So since it's totally without a doubt only rabbinic,
then in the absence of pubic hairs we can assume you're definitely
a minor and you can go ahead. So here again we said
a minute ago by רבא Rava that might be the חזקה chazakah
of רבא Rava would be a difference biblical and rabbinic. Now we're
saying the same is true about is the observed absence of pubic
hairs enough to prove she's a minor? And the answer is yes
for rabbinic laws, no for biblical laws. Okay so both the חזקה
chazakah and the observed absence are good for rabbinic laws, they're not
sufficient evidence for biblical laws. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara goes
on. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, הקדיש ואכל לוקה. hikdish ve'achal
lokei. Look, and now we're getting back so that was extremely important
discussion for the halakhic definition of adulthood and the connection between when
did the pubic hairs come, the relation of the pubic hairs and
the age and assumptions we can make if you didn't see them,
things we have to be concerned about if you saw that they
weren't there. Now we get back to the question of making a
vow. And the גמרא Gemara has a fascinating set of linked questions
which it has in other places as well. If you can make
a vow a year before your בר בת מצוה Bar Bat Mitzvah
and it's binding, does that mean you're considered an adult for all
purposes for the laws of vows? And one big question is, think
about a big נפקא מינה nafka mina whether you'd be considered an
adult. So I made a vow and I made this thing הקדש
hekdesh or I made it a forbidden to me as a נדר
neder and I'm only a year before my בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah.
If I'm an adult, not only does that thing become הקדש hekdesh
but what would be a consequence if I'm treated as an adult
for these laws? Can you imagine?
If I violated it, would I get lashes? Would within the laws
of vows for all purposes I'm considered an adult or just to
the extent that the vow takes effect? That's the question the גמרא
Gemara asks. Okay so let's take a look. אמר
רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: הקדיש ואכל לוקה. hikdish ve'achal lokei. If
you sanctified, meaning you made a vow and made the food forbidden
by a vow and then you ate it, you get lashes even
during this year prior. שנאמר: Shene'emar: איש כי יפלא לנדור, ish ki
yaflie lindor, if a man makes a vow, and we learn from
the word יפלא yaflie even the year before manhood or womanhood, even
the year before בר בת מצוה. Bar Bat Mitzvah. And then it
says ולא יחל דברו, ve'lo yechel devaro, actually it's a different פסוק,
pasuk, but anyway that you cannot violate your vow, meaning it's all
in the same פרשה. parsha. כל שישנו בהפלאה ישנו בבל יחל. Kol
sheyeshno behafla'ah yeshno be-lo yechel. If you can make a vow, you're
prohibited to violate it. וכל שאינו בהפלאה אינו בבל יחל, Vekol she'eino
behafla'ah eino be-lo yechel, if your vow won't be binding, אינו בבל
יחל eino be-lo yechel then you're not prohibited. But basically if you're
in the פרשה, parsha, you're in the פרשה. parsha. מתיב רב הונא
בר יהודה Motiv Rav Huna bar Yehuda to רב יהודה בר יהודה
Rav Yehuda bar Yehuda asks this סיועא לרב הונא si'uya le-Rav Huna
to prove רב הונא. Rav Huna. Now that's quite interesting. מתיב? Motiv?
Because there's no opposing opinion. I mean, there's an obvious logical position
that could argue on it, but anyway he's bringing a ברייתא braita
to support this idea but it's phrased as a question. He asks
to support. Let's see the ברייתא braita he brings. לפי שמצינו, Lefi
shematzinu, here's the ברייתא: braita: השוה הכתוב קטן כגדול לזדון שבועה לאיסור
לבל יחל. heshveh hakatuv katan kegadol le-zadon shvuah le-issur le-lo yechel. We
have found that the תורה Torah treats a minor, meaning the year
before, like an adult for the laws of willfully violating the oath,
that it's punishable, and for the prohibition, and for the prohibition of
בל יחל, lo yechel, which is the prohibition of לא יחל דברו.
lo yechel devaro. Okay so לא יחל דברו lo yechel devaro is
by a נדר, neder, by making something forbidden. זדון שבועה zadon shvuah
is an oath. I take an oath I won't do something and
I violate it, it's different than making an object forbidden. Anyway, we
see that the תורה Torah treats a minor like an adult, meaning
the year before. יכול, Yakhol, continues the ברייתא, braita, I might think
יהא חייב על הקדשו קרבן, yehayev al hektesho korban, if he violated
his something he sanctified, then he would also bring a קרבן korban
if he did it בשוגג. beshogeg. So maybe it even applies to
laws of קרבנות? korbanot? תלמוד לומר
זה הדבר. Talmud lomar zeh hadavar. This is the law, which is
the way it opens up the פרשה parsha of נדרים, nedarim, and
it's all about the prohibitions, not about קרבן. korban. So the main
point of this ברייתא braita is you're considered an adult for making
vows and for the prohibitions, but not for קרבן. korban. קרבן Korban
you have to be thirteen or twelve if you're a girl. Anyway,
קטן מיהא, katan miha, forget about קרבן korban for a minute. What
we have said in this ברייתא braita is לאיסור לבל יחל, le-issur
le-lo yechel, that even as a minor the prohibition you're prohibited and
you transgress בל יחל, lo yechel, which presumably means you get lashes.
So it says you're treated like an adult even as a minor.
for the year before, חייב *chayav*. So you see it's a proof
that you are you are treated as an adult. So no, אימא
לאיסור בל יחל *eima l'issur Bal Yachel*. No, it doesn't mean A
is prohibited and B you violate the biblical transgression of בל תאחר
*Bal Te'acher*. It means there's a there's a there's a problem of
בל יחל *Bal Yachel*, איסור בל יחל *issur Bal Yachel*, meaning it's
not biblical. It's it's like a rabbinic בל יחל *Bal Yachel*, combines
the two words. Not it's prohibited and it's בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*,
which would mean biblical. It's a problem of בל יחל *Bal Yachel*,
which means it's like a rabbinic problem. So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
איסור בל יחל ממה נפשך *issur Bal Yachel mamma nafshach*, make up
your mind. אי מופלא סמוך לאיש דאורייתא *ei mufla samuch l'ish d'Oraita*,
its status is biblical and presumably biblical not only to make your
vow effective but to treat you as an adult, so מילקא נמי
לילקי *milka nami lilki*, you should get lashes. ואי מופלא סמוך לאיש
לאו דאורייתא *v'ei mufla samuch l'ish lav d'Oraita*, and if you're not
an adult with for this law, meaning, you know, maybe even the
object doesn't become forbidden or maybe it does but you are not
treated fully as an adult, so איסור נמי ליכא *issur nami leika*.
So what type of oh there's some vague prohibition? If you're not
an adult, where's this vague prohibition going on? So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, okay, לאותן המוזהרין עליו *l'otan hamuzharin alav*. Fine. We don't mean
you're prohibited. Your vows might be binding or maybe they're not or
whatever, maybe it's all rabbinic, but certainly you as a minor are
not going to transgress and be punished. But it means the adults
around you, your parents, they can't let you transgress. Okay, and that's
what we mean איסור בל יחל *issur Bal Yachel*. Okay, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says, שמע מינה קטן אוכל נבילות בית דין מצווין עליו
להפרישו *shema mina katan ochel nevelot Beit Din mitzuvin alav l'hafrisho*. So
that would suggest that if a minor is doing sins, now the
parents might have a special obligation to stop their child from doing
sins because of the מצות חינוך *mitzvah chinuch*, but there's a general
debate if a minor's doing sins do other people have a responsibility
to stop him? It's not חינוך *chinuch*, but somehow there's a sense
of violation going on here that it's a communal responsibility. If anybody
ever had to deal with their kids in the playground and having
other adults give them advice about how to parent their kids, you
know that this might not always be so helpful. But anyway, but
that's what the parents are at what?
Or wanting to discipline your, yeah, exactly.
So well that's the flip side of it, I guess it depends
on what your experiences were. Anyway, so does בית דין *Beit Din*
have a מצוה *mitzvah* to intervene? So now you're saying, that's the
debate, so you're saying, oh the people around, they have to stop
you. You, you're a minor, you're not going to be prohibited, but
the people around have to stop you. Okay, but if you're saying
that, that sounds like there's a general principle that people have to
intervene. But that's debated, that might not be the case. So let's
see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. עכשיו
*achshav*, so is that true? הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהקדיש הוא ואכלו
אחרים *hacha b'mai askinan k'gon shehikdish hu v'achalu acherim*. No, no, no,
here's what we mean. Forget about that. It's not people stopping the
kid. What we mean is, yes, there is a prohibition of בל
תאחר *Bal Te'acher*, but not on the kid. Who's pro-, if the
kid goes ahead and makes this thing forbidden, who could transgress and
get lashes? The adults. Not that they have to stop the kid
from eating. They are bound by this הקדש *hekdesh* and they will
transgress בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*. And that's what we mean there's a
prohibition of בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*. Okay, even what, the kid might
not get lashes, he might be still considered a minor, but the
adults, they would. And that's the ברייתא *baraita* might be saying, the
adults might get lashes, but maybe they wouldn't bring the קרבן *korban*.
Maybe the status the kid gives is not 100 percent. But whatever
it is, we're talking about the adults getting lashes, not about the
kids getting lashes. Let me just read two more minutes to try
to get to a terminus, a somewhat ending point. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, הניחא למאן דאמר הקדיש הוא ואכלו אחרים לוקה *Haniha l'man
d'amar hikdish hu v'achalu acherim loke*. That's good if you say that
when the kid sanctified, he might not get lashes, he's still a
kid, but it's a binding status and other people get lashes. אלא
למאן דאמר אין לוקין מאי איכא למימר *Ella l'man d'amar ein lokin
mai ika l'meimar*? What do you say according to those that say
that even another person doesn't get lashes? That the whole status is
very, you know, not meaningful. דאיתמר *d'itmar*, it was taught, הקדיש הוא
ואכלו אחרים *hikdish hu v'achalu acherim*, this minor sanctified and other people
ate it. רב כהנא אמר אין לוקין *Rav Kahana amar ein lokin*,
other people don't get lashes. רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש אמרי תרוייהו לוקין
*Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish amri tarveihu lokin*, they say you do get
lashes. So if you say that even when he, not only does
he not get lashes, nobody can get lashes for what he does,
what do you do about the fact that the ברייתא *baraita* says
that there's a prohibition of בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*? So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא *miderabbanan v'kra asmachta b'alma*. Alright, that's
only rabbinic, really nobody violates בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*. So there now
is, and this is what we'll pick up with tomorrow, A, there's
a radical opinion that says not only is it binding but he's
considered a full adult for these laws and even as a minor
he would get lashes. But now we're having two other positions. One
is the interim, it's fully binding, he's not an adult, he doesn't
get lashes, other people get lashes. That's a very reasonable middle position.
But now we're going to get a third opinion which says this
whole thing really isn't biblical. We're saying he can make vows and
whatever, it really doesn't have biblical implications. He doesn't get lashes, other
people doesn't get lashes, and maybe the whole maybe the whole institution
is rabbinic. And we will pick up with that three-way debate tomorrow.